A sight for any surfer to behold. Board
riders making the most of dreamy
conditions at Alby's Middleton Beach.
But it wasn't always this way.
Lifelong surfer Peter Bolt grew up in
Albany and has walked this path to check
the surf more than most.
Observing little but unsurfable
closeouts at Middleton Beach for much of
that time. So for the past 30 years, he
helped spearhead efforts to do something
about it. I think I I came back to
Albany in 1990. We just felt that's
where we needed the juniors to have
something decent to surf at, you know,
in town where they can get access to.
>> Thanks to funding from the city of
Albany as well as the state and federal
governments. Specialist marine engineers
have created a perfect wave. The $13
million project involved the placement
of 70,000 tons of rock on the seabed.
There were times, however, when Peter
Bolt thought he'd never see it happen.
>> Peaks and troughs. peaks and troughs and
you know and roadblocks and mountains
you can't climb and it's just all too
hard. The Albany Surf Reef isn't without
its detractors who fear it'll affect the
beach in unwelcome ways. It was a waste
of money. But surfers are unperturbed,
saying the beach is holding up just fine
and it was worth every cent.
>> Well, I'm a surfer. I like a good wave.
Don't really care how much money was
spent.
We don't have many waves around here
that you've got like a really punchy top
to bottom takeoff wave and this wave is
that. It's a really high performance
wave.
>> Peter Bolt is similarly upbeat.
>> When I see the kids come down here
before school in the dark to get a wave
before they go to school and then they
zip down here again after school again.
Yeah, that's it. That's that's what this
was all about.
>> Making waves as a new generation hits
the water. Daniel Mercer, ABC News.